Okay בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is כ"ה, Chaf Hey,
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 25, we pick up at the very first
word on דף כ"ה עמוד א' daf Chaf Hey amud Aleph and
yesterday we've been dealing with or the last few days we've been
dealing with the whole issue about can you bring קרבנות korbanot from
animals of non-Jews, is there a פסוק pasuk that says that they
have to only be from Jewish ownership or is there a concern
of bestiality? Anyway and within that context it led to the whole
issue about the cows that were bringing back the ארון aron and
they sang and the way the פסוק pasuk was read was that
they burst out in song and there was a debate of ר'
אלעזר Rabbi Elazar and ר' שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani
so we're going to continue with some דרשות drashot of פסוקים psukim
and of miraculous stories and the debate of ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and ר' שמואל בר נחמני. Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani. So, וידם השמש,
Vayidom hashemesh, so this is by יהושע Yehoshua in the war that
he fought against the kings of כנען Kna'an and the sun was
still וירח עמד Vayarei'ach amad and the moon stood in place עד
יקום גוי אויביו Ad yikom goy oyvav until the nation took vengeance
from its enemies. הלא היא כתובה על ספר הישר Halo hi ktuvah
al sefer hayashar behold it is written on the book of the
righteous. So מאי ספר הישר, Mai sefer hayashar, what is the book
of the? So this is by the miracle that the sun stood
still in order to allow יהושע Yehoshua to finish the battle against
the enemies. So מאי ספר הישר, Mai sefer hayashar, what asks the
גמרא Gemara is the book of the righteous? אמר ר' חייא בר
אבא אמר ר' יוחנן Amar Rabbi Chiyya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan
זה ספר אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Ze sefer Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, this is
the book of the אבות, Avot, this is ספר בראשית Sefer Bereishit
שנקראו ישרים shenikru yesharim and they were called the righteous or the
upright, שנאמר תמות נפשי מות ישרים shene'emar tamut nafshi mot yesharim as
בלעם Bilam says let my soul die the death of the righteous.
Okay and somehow not exactly clear how we know that means אברהם
יצחק ויעקב Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov but since it's praising בני ישראל Bnei
Yisrael so and it's talking about like a selection of individuals who
are righteous presumably refers to אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov.
והיכא רמיזא, Heicha remiza, so if this idea that the sun stood
still was written in this ספר הישר, sefer hayashar, where is it
hinted in בראשית Bereishit that the sun would stand still for יהושע?
Yehoshua? So וזרעו
יהיה מלא הגוים V'zaro yihye mlo hagoyim where it says in בראשית
Bereishit with the blessing of אפרים Ephraim is that his descendants will
be the fill of the nations and יהושע Yehoshua was from אפרים.
Ephraim. אימתי יהיה מלא הגוים, Eimatai yihye mlo hagoyim, when will he
be the fill of the nations? בשעה שעמדה לו חמה ליהושע B'sha'ah
she'amdah lo chamma l'Yehoshua when the sun stood still because then the
all of the world knew about this miracle.
Okay ויעמד השמש בחצי השמים Vaya'amod hashemesh b'chatzi hashamayim and the sun
stood going back to this miracle in the center
of the heaven ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים v'lo atz lavo k'yom
tamim and it did not
descend down like as a full day. So the גמרא's Gemara understanding
that there were two moments in which the sun stood still, when
it was in the middle of the sky at the height of
the day at noon and then when it was about to set
it did not it stood there as well and it did not
set immediately and
so there's those two moments that it stood. So וכמה, V'kamma, so
how much was the time that it stood still? שאמר She'amar אמר
ר' יהושע בן לוי amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi עשרים וארבע שעי
esrim v'arba sha'ei twenty-four hours. So meaning it was twenty-four hours total
was the from sunrise to sunset of that day. אזל שית Azal
sheis it went six and then it was noon it was in
the middle of the sky וקם שית v'kam sheis and it stood
in the middle of the sky for six days. אזל שית Azal
sheis then it moved another six hours and it was about to
set וקם שית v'kam sheis and it stood there for six hours.
So כולי מלתא כיום תמים kulei milta k'yom tamim because it says
ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים v'lo atz lavo k'yom tamim and it
did not set for a full day so the entire passage of
the sun through the sky through the day through the sky in
the daytime what would have been twelve hours was twenty-four hours.
ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer אומר omer
says שלשים ושש shloshim v'sheish no the entire daytime there was thirty-six
hours. אזל שית Azal sheis it went six וקם תריסר v'kam treisar
it was twelve hours that it stood. אזל שית Azal sheis וקם
תריסר v'kam treisar and it went another six and then right when
it was at the horizon it stood for another twelve hours.
עמידתו כיום תמים. Amidato k'yom tamim. So yes יום תמים yom tamim
is twenty-four hours but the total time that it stood was twenty-four
hours plus the normal twelve hours of the day gives you thirty-six.
ר' שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani so here's the debate
of ר' אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and ר' שמואל בר נחמני. Rabbi Shmuel
bar Nachmani. ר' שמואל בר נחמני Rabbi Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר ארבעים
ושמונה amar arbaim v'shmonah, no no the whole day then was forty-eight
hours. אזל שית Azal sheis it went six וקם תריסר v'kam treisar
it stood for twelve hours. אזל שית Azal sheis וקם עשרים וארבע
v'kam arba esrim and it went for six and stood twenty-four hours
before setting. שנאמר ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים shene'emar v'lo atz lavo
k'yom tamim it did not move to set for a full day
so that last period where it was about to set and it
did not move to set for a full day there was twenty-four
hours. מכלל דמעיקרא לאו כיום תמים Michlal d'me'ikara lav k'yom tamim so
the previous standing was not twenty-four hours. Not exactly clear how we
know that it was half of that that it was twelve but
okay.
So now it
says רש"י Rashi tries to explain exactly where they got the idea
that it's half that and
twelve. איכא דאמרי בתוספתא Ika d'amrei b'Tosefta now some say this debate
twenty-four thirty-six forty-eight was not the total number of hours of the
day that they were discussing but the additional hours that. it stood.
Okay, פליגי. pligi. רבי יהושע בן לוי אומר עשרים וארבע. Rebbe Yehoshua
ben Levi omer esrim v'arba. רבי יהושע בן לוי Rebbe Yehoshua ben
Levi says 24. So before we thought that meant the total of
24, but now we're going to say an additional 24 hours. אזל
שית וקם תריסר, אזל שית וקם תריסר azal sheis v'kam treisar, azal
sheis v'kam treisar it went six and stood for 12, it went
six and stood for 12. עמידתו כיום תמים, amidaso k'yom tamim, so
the total amount was a, so the total amount of standing was
like a full day, 12 plus 12, 24, and that gets plus
the 12 of the day, 36. So now it's basically going to
be all the numbers we had before plus an additional 12, because
their numbers are going to be numbers of addition to the standard
12 hours of the day. כיום תמים. k'yom tamim. רבי אליעזר אומר
שלושים ושש, Rebbe Eliezer omer shloshim v'sheish, 36 additional hours. אזל שית
וקם תריסר, אזל שית וקם עשרים וארבע. azal sheis v'kam treisar, azal
sheis v'kam esrim v'arba. So again the 12 and the 24 standing.
ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים. v'lo atz lavo k'yom tamim. So the
setting, the pausing at the setting was 24 hours, but the standing
earlier wasn't that, so we'll assume it's half that, that gets you
36 hours of standing. ושמואל בר נחמני אמר עשרים וארבע, v'Shmuel bar
Nachmani amar esrim v'arba, I'm sorry, אמר amar ארבעים ושמונה, arba'im v'shmonah
48, but 48 additional hours.
אזל שית וקם עשרים וארבע, אזל שית וקם כ"ד. azal sheis v'kam
esrim v'arba, azal sheis v'kam chaf dalet. So both standing in the
middle of the sky and the standing before it setting was 24.
מקיש עמידה לביאה. makish amida l'viah. So we already established that before
it set it was 24 hours because ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים.
v'lo atz lavo k'yom tamim. And but that since it is the
פסוקים pesukim are parallel, ויעמוד בחצי ולא אץ לבוא כיום תמים, v'yaamod
b'chatzi v'lo atz lavo k'yom tamim, so therefore the same pausing that
it did at the before setting 24 hours was the pausing it
also did at the height of the sky. מה ביאה כיום תמים,
mah viah k'yom tamim, the same way right before setting it was
24 hours, אף עמידה כיום תמים, af amida k'yom tamim, even in
the middle of the sky it was 24 hours, a total of
48 additional, so a total of 60 hours of the day. Okay,
תנא: tana: כשם שעמדה לו חמה ליהושע, k'shem sheamda lo chama l'Yehoshua,
כך עמדה לו חמה למשה ולנקדימון
בן גוריון. kach amda lo chama l'Moshe ul'Nakdimon ben Guryon. The same
way the sun stood for יהושע, Yehoshua, it stood for משה, Moshe,
and it stood for נקדימון בן גוריון. Nakdimon ben Guryon. יהושע Yehoshua
קראי, kraei, in the יהושע Yehoshua that it stood, those are the
פסוקים pesukim that we read. נקדימון בן גוריון, Nakdimon ben Guryon, this
person נקדימון בן גוריון, Nakdimon ben Guryon, גמרא, Gemorah, that's a tradition,
and that's whatever, it's a whole other story that the גמרא Gemorah
has about him
in מסכת תענית. masechet Taanis. We won't worry about that. Some, some
person for whom a miracle was done and the sun stood. It's
funny, like some commoner. Okay,
גמרא: Gemorah: למשה מנלן? l'Moshe minalan? How do you know about משה?
Moshe? אתיא אחל אחל, asya acheil acheil, it's a גזירה שוה gezeira
shava to יהושע. Yehoshua. כתיב הכא אחל תת פחדך, kesiv hacha acheil
teis pachdicha, I will begin to give your fear, like when, and
this means that in the middle of the war that he did
against
סיחון מלך אמורי Sichon melech Emori ועוג מלך הבשן, v'Og melech haBashan,
also the sun stood still so he would have time to conquer
them and to wipe them out. So before that war God says
to משה, Moshe, I will begin to give your fear.
וכתיב התם ביהושע אחל גדלך, uch'siv hasam b'Yehoshua acheil gadlicha, I will
begin to make your name great. רבי יוחנן Rebbe Yochanan אמר אתיא
תת תת, amar asya teis teis, another גזירה שוה gezeira shava from
to give, to give. כתיב הכא במשה אחל תת פחדך, kesiv hacha
b'Moshe acheil teis pachdicha, I will place your fear. וכתיב ביהושע ביום
תת ה' את האמורי, uch'siv b'Yehoshua beyom teis Hashem es haEmori, at
the day that God gives the אמורי Emori before you. ושמואל בר
נחמני v'Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר, amar, and again here we have a
רבי אליעזר Rebbe Eliezer and רבי יהושע בן נחמני, Rebbe Yehoshua ben
Nachmani, oh no, here's ושמואל בר נחמני. v'Shmuel bar Nachmani. Do we
have a רבי אליעזר? Rebbe Eliezer? Not yet. Okay, ושמואל בר נחמני
v'Shmuel bar Nachmani אמר מגופיה דקרא שמיעא ליה, amar migufeih d'kra shamia
lei, you can learn it from the very פסוק pasuk itself, you
don't need a גזירה שוה gezeira shava that a similar miracle was
done for יהושע Yehoshua as it was done for משה, Moshe, or
for משה Moshe as it was done for יהושע. Yehoshua. אשר ישמעון
שמעך ורגזו וחלו מפניך, asher yishm'un shim'acha v'ragzu v'chalu mipanecha, so
God says that they will hear of your report and they will
fear and tremble before you. אימתי רגזו וחלו מפניך? eimasai ragzu v'chalu
mipanecha? בשעה שעמדה לו חמה למשה. beshaa sheamda lo chama l'Moshe. So
it says because that's the end of the פסוק, pasuk, right? It
says אחל תת פחדך ויראתך על פני העמים אשר ישמעון שמעך ורגזו
וחלו מפניך. acheil teis pachdicha v'yiracha al penei ha'amim asher yishm'un shim'acha
v'ragzu v'chalu mipanecha. So what would make them that fear and tremble
in terms of this what he's about to do with עוג מלך
הבשן Og melech haBashan and סיחון מלך אמורי? Sichon melech Emori? It
must be a similar thing that was done to יהושע, Yehoshua, the
fear and the trembling that came as a result of this miracle.
בשעה שעמדה לו חמה למשה. beshaa sheamda lo chama l'Moshe. Fine. So
now the גמרא Gemorah says like this: מיתיבי, meisivei, I'll challenge you
on this: ולא היה כיום ההוא לפניו ואחריו. v'lo haya k'yom hahu
lifanav v'acharav.
It says by יהושע Yehoshua no day was like this before and
after. So this miracle that was done to יהושע Yehoshua was unprecedented.
And here you're saying that it actually was preceded by משה Moshe
and afterwards by this נקדימון בן גוריון. Nakdimon ben Guryon. So אי
בעית אימא שעות הוא דלא הוו נפישי כולי האי. ei bayis eima
sha'os hu d'lo havo nefishei kulei hai. Fine. It was unprecedented in
terms of the number of hours. Yes, other people the sun stood
for, but no one as long as for יהושע. Yehoshua. ואי בעית
אימא v'ei bayis eima if you want you could say, אבני ברד
לא הוו. avnei barad lo havo. And by יהושע Yehoshua not only
did the sun stand still, but these hailstones came down to aid
him, and that was not for משה. Moshe. דכתיב ויהי בנסם מפני
בני ישראל הם במורד בית חורון וה' השליך עליהם אבנים גדולות מן
השמים עד עזקה וימתו. d'chsiv v'yehi b'nusam mipnei benei Yisrael hem b'morad
beis Choron v'Hashem hishlich aleihem avanim gedolos min hashamayim ad Azeka v'yamusu.
It was when they were running away from the children of ישראל,
Yisrael, they were in the descent of בית חורון, Beis Choron, God
cast upon them great hailstones until עזקה Azeka and they died. Okay,
so it's interesting. So the גמרא Gemara wants to sort of you
know here the whole point by יהושע Yehoshua is how is יהושע
Yehoshua going to fill the place of משה, Moshe, right, like how
do you fill the shoes of somebody the larger than life figure?
So there's this tremendous miracle that was done for יהושע Yehoshua that
was never done like this. The פסוק pasuk says anywhere before or
after, you know, not even for משה. Moshe. So it's a little
bit maybe the גמרא Gemara wants to, I don't know, not, you
know, feel that he's surpassed משה Moshe to that degree, wants to
put משה, Moshe, no no no, something like this did happen for
משה, Moshe, but still allow יהושע Yehoshua to have been greater, you
know, as the פסוקים pesukim make it clear in certain ways. I
can't exactly understand why it's important for the גמרא, Gemara, you know,
this understanding about this נקדימון בן גוריון. Nakdimon ben Guryon. Anyway, fine.
ו׳ v' okay. כתיב. ktiv. Now we're going to do another דרשא
drasha on פסוקים pesukim and another debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
and רב שמואל בר נחמני. Rav Shmuel bar Nachmani. Also about, you
know, on these sort of פסוקים. pesukim. ויאמר ללמד בני יהודה קשת
הנה כתובה על ספר הישר Vayomer l'lamed b'nei Yehudah kashet hinei k'tuvah
al Sefer HaYashar and also on the mentioning of ספר הישר. Sefer
HaYashar. Okay, so this is by the, you know,
in שמואל ב׳, Shmuel Bet, the beginning of to teach the children
of יהודה Yehudah the, you know, archery, הנה כתובה על ספר הישר,
hinei k'tuvah al Sefer HaYashar, behold it is written on the book
of the הישר. Yashar. מאי ספר הישר? Mai Sefer HaYashar? What is
the ספר הישר? Sefer HaYashar? אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי
יוחנן זה ספר אברהם יצחק ויעקב. Amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar
Rabbi Yochanan zeh sefer Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov. Like we said before, it's
בראשית. Bereishit. שנקראו ישרים Shenikru yesharim because they were called upright, דכתיב
בהו תמות נפשי מות ישרים ותהי אחריתי כמהו. dich'tiv behu tamut nafshi
mot yesharim ut'hi achriti kamoho. והיכא רמיזא? V'heicha r'miza?
So where is it hinted in בראשית Bereishit that יהודה Yehudah would
be the archers? יהודה אתה יודוך אחיך Yehudah atah yoducha achecha
because it says by the ברכה bracha that he received, you know,
יהודה, Yehudah,
you, your brothers will, you know, you know, will praise you, ידך
בעורף אויביך, yadcha b'oref oyvecha, your hand is against the neck of
your enemy. ואיזו היא מלחמה שצריכה יד כנגד עורף? V'eizu hi milchamah
shet'richah yad k'neged oref?
So what is a type of a war that you have your
hand opposite the back of the neck? Now this is not the
back of the neck of the enemy, but this is the back
of your own neck. הוי אומר זה קשת. Hevei omer zeh kashet.
It's archery when you pull the bow back, the hand holding onto
the arrow to the, you know, is being pulled back and that
gets to the back of your neck. So that's ידך בעורף yadcha
b'oref except not just אויביך. oyvecha. Okay.
Okay. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
זה ספר משנה תורה. zeh Sefer Mishneh Torah. No, no, no, the
here at least ספר הישר Sefer HaYashar refers to דברים. Devarim. ואמאי
קרו ליה ספר הישר? V'amai karu lei Sefer HaYashar?
Why is it called the book of the righteous or the upright?
דכתיב ועשית הישר והטוב dich'tiv v'asita hayashar v'hatov because דברים Devarim opens
with you shall do what is right and good. So there's the
whole sense of that like sort of moral mandate is in דברים
Devarim בעיני ה׳ והיכא רמיזא? b'einei Hashem v'heicha r'miza? So where is
it hinted in דברים Devarim that יהודה, Yehudah, the children of יהודה
Yehudah are archers? והיכא רמיזא, V'heicha r'miza, ידיו רב לו ועזר מצריו
תהיה. yadav rav lo v'ezer mitzarav tihyeh.
That's what it says by the ברכה bracha of יהודה Yehudah in
דברים. Devarim. His hand will be great for him. ואיזו היא מלחמה
שצריכה שתי ידים? V'eizu hi milchamah shet'richah shtei yadayim? So it's ידיו
yadav in the plural, his hands.
What is a type of a warfare that you need to use
both hands? Because you know, like a sword or a lance you
basically use one hand. So what do you need to use both
hands? הוי אומר זה קשת, Hevei omer zeh kashet, that is archery
because one hand holds the bow and one hand, you know, pulls
the string. Okay. רב שמואל בר נחמני אמר זה ספר שופטים. Rav
Shmuel bar Nachmani amar zeh Sefer Shoftim. No, ספר הישר Sefer HaYashar
refers to the Book of Judges. ואמאי קרו ליה ספר הישר? V'amai
karu lei Sefer HaYashar?
Why is it called the ספר הישר? Sefer HaYashar? דכתיב בימים ההם
אין מלך בישראל איש הישר בעיניו יעשה. dich'tiv bayamim hahem ein melech
b'Yisrael ish hayashar b'einav ya'aseh. So that's a little ironic, right, the
recurring theme of שופטים Shoftim is everybody would do whatever they want
because there was no central authority, there was no king. It's the
book of the הישר Yashar because everybody was doing what was הישר
בעיניו. hayashar b'einav.
Okay. So where in שופטים Shoftim is this idea hinted to, that
יהודה Yehudah would be archers? והיכא רמיזא, V'heicha r'miza, למען דעת דורות
בני ישראל ללמדם מלחמה, l'maan da'at dorot b'nei Yisrael l'lamdam milchamah,
in order to teach the generations of ישראל Yisrael to make war.
ואיזו היא מלחמה שצריכה לימוד? V'eizu hi milchamah shet'richah limud? What type
of warfare requires like real training? Apparently, you know, the type of
warfare that they did in the ancient times, you know, did not
require extensive training. But what type of a warfare would require extensive
training? שצריכה לימוד, Shet'richah limud, הוי אומר זה קשת, hevei omer zeh
kashet, that's learning how to be an archer. Now, that speaks about
the children of ישראל. Yisrael. ממאי דביהודה כתיב? Mimai d'viYehudah ktiv? How
do you know that when we're talking about people that waged war,
we're primarily focusing on יהודה? Yehudah? דכתיב Dich'tiv because it also says
in שופטים, Shoftim, מי יעלה לנו אל הכנעני להלחם בו בתחלה? mi
ya'aleh lanu el haK'naani l'hilachem bo bat'chilah? Who shall rise up to
go first? ויאמר ה׳ יהודה יעלה. Vayomer Hashem Yehudah ya'aleh. יהודה Yehudah
will go first. Since they're the ones that would lead the people
in war, so when it's talking about warfare primarily it's focusing on
the children of יהודה. Yehudah. Okay. One more debate of פסוקים. pesukim.
וירם הטבח את השוק והעליה Vayarem hatabach et hashok v'ha'alyah וישם לפני
שאול vayasem lifnei Shaul
and the butcher, you know, rose up the, the calf and the
עליה, alyah, the thing that was the, the elevated thing, and put
it before שאול. Shaul. מאי והעליה? Mai v'ha'alyah? What is this עליה?
alyah? רבי יוחנן אומר שוק. Rabbi Yochanan omer shok. That is shok,
excuse me, שוק. shok. מה והאליה? Ma veha'alyah? What is this אליה?
alyah? רבי יוחנן אומר Rabbi Yochanan omer שוק, shoke, that is שוק,
shoke, excuse me.
שוק ואליה. Shoke ve'alyah.
So the שוק shoke is the שוק, shoke, the calf is the
calf, but the אליה alyah is the אליה, alyah, the fat tail
that you would have of a sheep.
מה והאליה דמסמכה שוק ואליה? Ma veha'alyah d'msamcha shoke ve'alyah? Because the
calf is next to the fat tail. So עליה, aleha, like it's
עליה aleha and אליה. alyah. You know, what is on it? What
is above it? רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, so Rabbi Eliezer
says שוק וחזה. shoke vechazeh. No, it is the calf and the
breast. מה והאליה דמנח ליה לחזה עילויה דשוק Ma veha'alyah d'machis lechazeh
iluyei d'shoke because the breast was put on top of the calf,
you know, when they would do a waving for the שלמים. shelamim.
כי בעי נופי מנפי ליה, Ki ba'ei nufei manflei, when you would
have to wave it. רב שמעון בר נחמני אמר Rav Shimon bar
Nachmani amar שוק ושופי. shoke veshufi. No, no, it is talking about
the calf and the שופי, shufi, which רש"י Rashi says basically is
like the thigh. מה והאליה שופי עילויה דשוקא היא, Ma veha'alyah shufi
iluyei d'shokai, because the thigh is above the calf. Okay. So that
was a whole דרשות drashos of פסוקים pesukim and debates of רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רב שמעון בר נחמני Rav Shimon bar Nachmani
and also רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. All right, now we're back to
our משנה. Mishna. לא תתייחד אשה עמהם, Lo tityached isha imahem, a
woman should not be in private with non-Jews because afraid of that
they, you know, of
licentiousness, afraid either about rape or seduction, they'll take advantage of her
sexually. So the גמרא Gemara says במאי עסקינן? bemai askinan? What's the
scenario about being with a non-Jew? אילימא בחד, Ileima bechad, one man?
דכי פריצי גבי ישראל מי שרי? D'chafsei gabei Yisrael mishari? So then
it's not about a non-Jew. A Jewish woman is not allowed to
be in private even with a Jewish man. והתנן, Vehatnan, we taught
in the משנה, Mishna, לא יתייחד איש אחד עם שתי נשים. lo
yityached ish echad im shtei nashim. One man can't be with two
women and certainly not just with one woman because there's concerns, that's
classic ייחוד. yichud. So what's the scenario that it's permissible by a
Jew but not permissible by a non-Jew? Top of כ"ה עמוד ב'.
chaf-hey amud bet.
אלא בתלתא, Ela betlosa, okay we'd be talking about that it would
be three men, okay, because sometimes in the daytime it could be
one woman and two men, in the nighttime one woman and three
men because you're afraid that one of them will, you know, have
to go to the bathroom or whatever, go to sleep. So anyway,
go to the bathroom primarily. Anyway, so therefore in a case where
there's multiple men where it would be okay for ישראל, Yisrael, it's
not okay if they're non-Jews. דכי פריצי גבי ישראל... D'chafsei gabei Yisrael...
so the גמרא Gemara says one minute, it's
still not specifically about them being a non-Jew because דכי פריצי גבי
ישראל בפרוצים מי שרי? d'chafsei gabei Yisrael bepruzim mishari? But even if
it was a Jew, if it was a Jew who is not,
who was considered like, you know,
not,
I've got to look for the right word here, not exactly licentious,
but anyway, you know, sexually free behavior, somebody who was not, did
not keep a sexual morality and basically like slept around and so
on. So for a person like that, even a Jew, you know,
a woman cannot be with two or three Jewish men in that
case. והתנן, Vehatnan, we taught in the משנה, Mishna, אבל אשה אחת
מתייחדת עם שני אנשים. aval isha achas mityachedes im shnei anashim. A
woman can be with two men in the daytime. ואמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל, Ve'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel, רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav
Yehuda amar Shmuel said in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, לא שנו
אלא בכשרים, lo shanu ela bichesherim, that's only if they are, you
know, כשרים, kesherim, meaning that they are people that are good and
morally upright and don't, are not sexually loose. That's a good one,
loose. אבל בפרוצים, Aval bepruzim, people that are sexually loose, אפילו עשרה
נמי לא. afilu asara nami lo. Can't even be a woman with
even ten men. מעשה היה, Maaseh haya, and there was a story
והוציאוה עשרה במטה. vetziuha asara bemitta. And ten took a woman out
in a מטה. mitta. Now what exactly that means is not clear.
רש"י Rashi says it means that ten men smuggled a woman out
of the city, you know, they like, they said she maybe was
dead, like let it look like a coffin or something, whatever it
was,
and so that they all could have like some group orgy or
something. רש"י Rashi sort of makes it sound like maybe the woman
was willing. You could also imagine this
could terrific, it brings up images also of like of a case
of rape and of a group rape and terrible images of that
nature. So anyway, that's also generally a question about whether ייחוד yichud
is more about seduction or it's more about rape. But anyway, so
you don't have to be a non-Jew, right? Certainly we're considering non-Jews
to be sexually loose, but then why is it specifically saying a
woman can't be with a non-Jew? It should just, you know, it's
not specifically about being non-Jewish, it's just being about sexually loose. So
the גמרא Gemara says, where was I?
לא צריכא, Lo tzricha, you need it for the following case. באשתו
עמו, Be'ishto imo, that it's a man even a man who is
sexually loose but his wife is with him.
So the assumption is that if it's a man and his wife,
another woman could be with them and the wife will make sure
or he'll be concerned about the wife and she'll make sure that
he's not going to sleep with this other woman. And that would
be true even by somebody that would be considered a פרוץ. parutz.
But, so that's for a Jew. But in the case of a
non-Jew, even with his wife with him, we would not allow it.
עובד כוכבים אין אשתו משמרתו, Oveid kochavim, ein ishto mshamaroslo,
if it's a non-Jew, we do not trust his wife to keep
him in check. אבל ישראל אשתו משמרתו, Aval Yisrael, ishto mshamaroslo, but
by a Jew, his wife keeps. We trust him to keep his,
his wife to keep him in check even if he is a
פרוץ. parutz. So that's why we have to say she cannot be
with a non-Jew even in the best of circumstances. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, וטיפוק ליה משום שפיכות דמים, Vetipok lei
mishum shfichus damim, right this should be the obvious question. If a
woman can't be, the next part of the משנה Mishna says that
a man can't be alone with a non-Jew because you're afraid that
he'll kill him. So why do you have to mention the concern
about, you know, about sex by a woman? Why isn't it just
any Jew, man or woman can't be with a non-Jew, you're afraid
that they'll be killed? What's, what,
what does it add anything to say that there's this concern with
a woman about, you know, seduction or rape? So the גמרא Gemara
says, וטיפוק ליה משום שפיכות דמים, Vetipok lei mishum shfichus damim, where
were we?
אמר רבי ירמיה באשה חשובה עסקינן. Amar Rebbi Yirmiyah b’isha chashuva askinan.
We're talking about a woman who is, has status. Okay? דמירסתי מינה,
Demirsasi mina, they're afraid of her. You know, somebody that's an important
person, they're, we're not afraid that that person will get killed, you
know, if they're alone with a non-Jew, man or woman. You know,
they don't want to get repercussions from the government or whatever, somebody
the government will care of that was killed. But we are, so
therefore that would, there would not be a problem about being alone
with them in terms of a concern of being killed. But in
the case of a woman, we are case concerned about, you know,
sexual misconduct. Now why? Wouldn't they be afraid that they would hear
from it from the government in that case as well? So it
could be here that it's maybe as רש"י Rashi indicates it would
be a concern of seduction, not rape. So therefore, if it's an
important person, we're not concerned about murder, maybe we're not concerned about
rape, but we
would be concerned about seduction, and that's why the woman cannot be
alone with them. Okay, or maybe it'll be rape, but they'll claim
it was seduction, it's still going to be different than murder. That's
what רבי ירמיה Rebbi Yirmiyah says. רב אידי אמר אשה כלי זיינה
עליה. Rav Idi amar isha klei zayna aleha. רב אידי Rav Idi
says a woman, her weapons are on her. Now what does this
mean? So, you know, so there's a slight debate here of רש"י
Rashi and תוספות. Tosfos. You know,
רש"י Rashi basically says that it means that people, they won't be
interested in killing her. They'll want, they'll be more interested in having
sex with her. So therefore it's not a concern of murder, it
would just be a concern of sex because that's just the reality.
Maybe you know, again, maybe they see men as threats, so they
want to kill men. Women they want to see as a sexual
object. Okay. תוספות Tosfos gives a different explanation. You know, one thing
תוספות Tosfos says is he quotes a ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, which is actually
quite interesting, which is, which says that, I'm not sure exactly fits
the idea that her weapons are on her, but the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
says that a woman could claim to be a non-Jew. You know,
a man is circumcised, he can't claim. A woman could claim to
be a non-Jew. So there's not a fear that they'll murder her
because they'll think she's a non-Jew, but it's not, but in terms
of sex that has nothing to do with being Jewish. You know,
the concern of seduction and rape is still what it was. Okay,
so that's, so that's what תוספות Tosfos says. He has some other
explanations as well, but we'll go with that. So now the גמרא
Gemara says, מאי בינייהו. Mai beinaihu. So what difference does it make
which of these two explanations we give? We have two reasons why
they, what the case is for why a woman it's not a,
you know, we're not dealing with a concern that she'll be murdered.
One is it's a היכי תימצי heichi timtzi specifically about an important
woman, and the other is it's generally not a concern about women.
Okay, but either way, it's either a concern of murder or of,
you know, sexual misconduct, seduction, rape. So what difference does it make
which reasons we give? So the גמרא Gemara says, מאי בינייהו איכא
בינייהו אשה חשובה בין הנשים ושאינה
חשובה בין הנשים. Mai beinaihu ika beinaihu isha chashuva bein hanashim v’she’eina
chashuva bein hanashim. Now I'm going to read this like תוספות. Tosfos.
רש"י Rashi has a very difficult way of reading it. I'll just
sort of say for the record that רש"י Rashi reads חשובה בין
הנשים chashuva bein hanashim means a woman that is seen as important
amongst women, means an attractive woman. And then רש"י Rashi goes on
to assume that people won't rape an attractive woman, unattractive woman, excuse
me. But we're going to bracket רש"י's Rashi’s explanation. תוספות Tosfos reads
this in a much better way. And it's not amongst who is
she considered חשוב, chashuv, it is no, she is a חשובה chashuva
woman
and now who is she being in ייחוד yichud with? Okay? So
תוספות Tosfos says like this: אשה חשובה, Isha chashuva, if it is
an important woman, and she is בין אנשים, bein anashim, and she
is among men. So, an important woman among men, we already said
that according to, you know, רבי ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmiyah, there's not a
concern that she'll be murdered, right, because she's important. But רבי ירמיה
Rebbi Yirmiyah said that was exactly the case of the משנה Mishna
where there is a concern of sexual misconduct, of seduction or rape.
So for רבי ירמיה, Rebbi Yirmiyah, an important woman among men, she
can't be in ייחוד yichud because of a concern of seduction or
rape. But, you know, but רב אידי, Rav Idi, he didn't sort
of make it about the circumstances, like important, not important, this, that.
He just said it's never a concern for a woman. Murder is
never a concern, the only concern is seduction or rape. type. So
for him that he did not make it contextual and based on
circumstances, for him an important woman, okay, would be still a concern
of wait minute let me see if I get this right.
Okay, so I said that so I said that a little wrong.
Let me go back. For רב ירמיה Reb Yirmiya as I said
that אשה חשובה isha chashuva he said specifically is a case where
there's not a concern of murder but that is the case of
the משנה Mishna that is a concern of sex. And you know
for רב אידי Rav Idi who says אשה כלי זיין עליה, isha
klei zayin ala, which means they'll never want to kill her, okay
either for the reason that I said that you know that she
can pretend that she's not Jewish or because you know she's a
woman, they're not afraid of her, they're not going to want to
kill her, they'll have compassion on her, they don't see her as
a threat. So that's never a concern. But he so he would
so he could claim that if she's also חשובה, chashuva, if she
also has status, then they wouldn't try to you know then there
would not be a concern of sex, certainly not a concern of
rape. So רב ירמיה Reb Yirmiya specifically had said
that there is still a concern about sex or of rape or
seduction in that case, but you know רב אידי Rav Idi could
claim no, in a case of חשובה chashuva there would not be
a concern of sex at all. So that would be one case
of חשובה שנמצאת בין אנשים chashuva she-nimtzeit bein anashim ושאינה חשובה בין
אנשים. ve-she-einah chashuva bein anashim. Similarly a woman who does not have
status that can she be מתייחדת mityachedet amongst women? So for you
know רב ירמיה, Reb Yirmiya, you know רב ירמיה Reb Yirmiya would
say well if she's not חשובה chashuva then there's a concern of
murder and women will kill her also. So for him the answer
would be no. But for רב אידי Rav Idi who says no
no no there's never a concern for women that she'll be murdered,
so not a concern of murder, the only concern is sex, and
a woman amongst women there's no concern of sex. Okay, so that
would be cases where according to רב אידי Rav Idi there would
not be concerns, but according to רב ירמיה Reb Yirmiya there would
be concerns.
תניא כוותיה דרב אידי בר אבין Tani ke-vatea d-Rav Idi bar Avin
we taught like רב אידי בר אבין Rav Idi bar Avin האישה
אף על פי ששלום עמה לא תתייחד עמהן מפני שחשודין על העריות.
ha-isha af al pi she-shalom ima lo tityached imahen mipnei she-chashudin al
ha-arayot. A woman even though you know there is שלום עמה shalom
ima she should not have ייחוד yichud with them because of the
עריות. arayot. So the language of אף על פי ששלום עמה af
al pi she-shalom ima sounds like categorically for women we are not
concerned that she will be killed, they're not a threat, and nevertheless
there's an איסור ייחוד, issur yichud, so it's a fundamental categorical point
that we are not concerned that they will be killed. Okay now
we move on to the next part which is about ייחוד yichud
of a man or of anybody you know whatever a man and
a concern of being killed. לא יתייחד אדם עמהם. lo yityached adam
imahem. תנו רבנן Tanu rabbanan our rabbis taught ישראל שנזדמן לו עובד
כוכבים בדרך. Yisrael she-nizdamen lo oved kochavim ba-derech. So if a Jew
bumped into a non-Jew on the way and they were sort of
walking along the way, so what are you supposed to do? There
you are alone, nobody else is around, you're not you have to
be afraid that he might try to kill her, what are you
supposed to do? So טופלו לימינו, toflo limino, you make sure that
he walks on your right hand side. Why is that? רב שמעון
בנו של רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא אומר Rav Shimon b'no shel Rebbi
Yochanan ben Broka omer so רב שמעון בנו של רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקא Reb Shimon b'no shel Rebbi Yochanan ben Broka spells it out
or and you know says בסייף be-sayif if the guy is wearing
a sword because in those days you know people walked around armed,
not like nowadays, nobody walks around armed haha anyway there the people
went around with a girded with a sword, so if he's wearing
a sword so where's his sword going to be? His sword
is going to be on his left side because you know if
you're a righty, you know you'll stick your right arm to your
left side to draw your sword out of the sheath. So if
he's wearing a sword טופלו לימינו toflo limino then you have him
walk on your right, so then his left where his sword is
is against you on your right, so if he tries to move
his right arm you know to grab his sword you'll be right
there and able to stop it.
במקל be-makkel however if he's walking with a stick right and he's
holding the stick in his in you know then טופלו לשמאלו toflo
lismolo then have him go to your left because if he's walking
with a stick he's holding with his dominant hand, his right hand,
and then he can just you know if he's on your right
side he can just take a stick and whack you, but if
he's on your left side then where his stick is and where
his right arm is it's against you, so you know he won't
be able to get access, you'll be able to block it you
know in a much easier way. Okay היו עולין במעלה hayu olin
bama-ale if they
were you were going up an incline, going up a mountain או
יורדין בירידה o yordin beyerida or going down a mountain לא יהא
ישראל למטה ועובד כוכבים למעלה lo yehei Yisrael lemata ve-oved kochavim lemala
the Jew should not be below and the non-Jew above whether you
know whether going up the non-Jew should not be ahead of you
and the top or whether going down he shouldn't be behind you
he shouldn't be higher up אלא ישראל למעלה ועובד כוכבים למטה ela
Yisrael lemala ve-oved kochavim lemata the Jew should be above and the
non-Jew below so it's not exactly clear because if he's behind you
you know could attack you without you knowing about it, but presumably
the point is is that you know it's better to have the
higher position, that's always the more advantageous position, and רש"י Rashi basically
says you should not let him go totally behind you you know
should still try to arrange that he's on your right or your
left or so on but still better that you maintain the higher
position ואל ישוח לפניו ve-al yishach le-fanav and Do not bow down
in front of him, like you know to pick up some money
or to tie your shoe, שמא ירוצץ גולגלתו shema yerotzetz gulgolto maybe
he'll crush your head. All right, so a lot of clearly fears
and concerns about that non-Jews would use any opportunity to kill a
Jew. שאלו להיכן הולך sha'alu le'heichan holeich and the non-Jew says, "Hey
where you going?" ירחיב לו את הדרך yarchiv lo et haderech you
should extend the way, meaning you should say, "Oh you know
I'm getting off at... you know you're going from I don't know
let's say New York to DC, you should say I'm getting off
at Philadelphia." All right, I'm sorry, you know you're saying from New
York to Philadelphia, you say I'm getting off at DC. So therefore
he'll you know when you get to Philadelphia he'll think he has
plenty of time to do whatever mischief he wants to do to
you and because he still thinks he's got a few hours left
and then you get off at Philadelphia you managed to avoid him
that way, you know avoid him using the opportunity to hurt you
because he thought
he had more time. ירחיב לו את הדרך yarchiv lo et haderech
כדרך שעשה יעקב אבינו לעשו הרשע kederech she'asah Yaakov Avinu le'Esav haRasha
דכתיב dechtiv עד אשר אבוא אל אדוני שעירה, ad asher avo el
adoni Se'irah, "No you go ahead, I'll catch up to you in
Seir." Now that was a little different because he actually manipulated it
so he didn't have to be walking with Esav all together, but
anyway, וכתיב vechtiv ויעקב נסע סוכתה, veYaakov nasa Succotah, but he didn't
go to Seir, he stopped at Succoth, he never made it to
Seir. Okay. מעשה בתלמידי רבי עקיבא שהיו הולכים לכזיב. ma'aseh betalmidei Rabbi
Akiva shehayu holchim leChziv. So the students of Rabbi Akiva were going
to Chziv, which was north of Israel but a little bit short
of Akko,
which was the northernmost city. פגע בהן ליסטים paga bahen listim and
then these bandit men approached them, you know, and maybe they were
you know weren't making it immediately obvious that they were trying to
rob him and they were just you know accompanying them, walking in
the same direction. אמר להם לאן אתם הולכים, amar lahem le'an atem
holchim, "Where are you going?" אמרו לו לעכו, amru lo le'Akko, they
said we're going to Akko, which was even further than Chziv. כיון
שהגיעו לכזיב keivan shehigi'u leChziv when they got to Chziv, פרשו, parshu,
they said "Okay, you know what, actually we're here at Chziv, we
got to where we wanted." אמר להם תלמידי מי אתם, amar lahem
talmidei mi atem, so these bandit men said to them, "Who students
are you?" אמרו לו תלמידי רבי עקיבא, amru lo talmidei Rabbi Akiva,
we're students of Rabbi Akiva. אמרו להם amru lahem they said, אשרי
רבי עקיבא ותלמידיו ashrei Rabbi Akiva vetalmidav praised should be Rabbi Akiva
and his students שלא פגע בהן אדם רע מעולם shelo paga bahen
adam ra me'olam that he obviously taught you how to deal with
you know nefarious no-good people such as us and and you know
and his advice clearly saved you from you know from suffering any
harm, you're pretty you're wise to our ways. Now another story, רבי
מנשיא הוה אזיל לבי תורסא, Rabbi Menasha hava azil lebei Torsa, Rabbi
Menasha was going to this place called Bei Torsa. פגעו בו גנבי
paga'u vo ganvei and also robbers approached him. Apparently for whatever reason
they weren't prepared to rob him right away but he was afraid
they would find an opportunity. אמרו לו לאן את אזיל amru lo
le'an at azil they said to him, "Where are you going?" אמר
להם לפומבדיתא amar lahem lePumbedita to Pumbedita, which was further distance than
Torsa. כי מטא לבי תורסא ki mata lebei Torsa when they came
to Bei Torsa, so פרש, parash, he said "Okay, here's where I'm
going." אמרו לו תלמידו דיהודה
רמאה את, amru lo talmido deYehuda rama'a at, "Oh you must be
a student of Yehuda the deceptive one, the sly one," a student
of Rabbi Yehuda, but they didn't even call him Rabbi Yehuda and
they called him the רמאה rama'a you know the deceptive one, "You
tricked us." So as opposed to the previous story said, "Oh your
Rabbi was great, I mean you know like he taught you how
to avoid the likes of us," here was, "Oh your Rabbi is
a deceiver he and you tricked us." אמר להו amar lahu so
he said to them, ידעיתו ליה, yedaitu leih, "You know who he
is? You know Rabbi Yehuda and this too you're going to call
him a
רמאה?" rama'a? יהא רעוא דליהוו הנהו אינשי בשמתא, yehei ra'ava deleihavu hanu
inshi beshamta, these people you, you גנבים, ganavim, you should be under
חרם cherem of Rabbi Yehuda's חרם cherem if this is the you
know the disrespect that you are showing him. אזלו עבדו גנבותא עשרין
ותרין שנין azlu avdu ganvuta esrin utarin shanin they went and they
continued writing to do their you know burglary profession for the next
22 years, ולא אצלח velo atzlach
and they didn't succeed because they were under the שמתא shamta they
were under you know the חרם cherem and that affected their success
in their burglary. So כיון דחזו keivan dechazu once they realized something
was up and they must have realized that it must have had
something to do with this you know חרם cherem that they were
put under, אתו כולהו תבו שמתייהו atu kulhu tavu shamtayeihu they all
went and they asked for מחילה mechila and they asked to have
their חרם cherem removed. It's pretty funny you know move
the חרם cherem from them because now they are showing remorse for
their disrespect, but obviously their goal is to be able to be
more successful in their robbery so it raises interesting questions about agreeing
to remove it under those circumstances. But anyway, והוה בהדי חד גירדנא
vehavah bahadei chad giridna and there was amongst them like you know
one like weaver, דלא אתא לשרויי שמתיה delo ata lishruyei shamtiah and
he did not you know he didn't bother to come to get
his חרם cherem removed. אכליה אריה achleih aryeh so a lion ate
him. Okay. היינו דאמרי אינשי hainu de'amri inshi that's what people say,
גירדנא דלא טיבזן giridna delo tivzan you know a a
a weaver you know who is Rashi says that means that is
you know, that's like, that's not,
that's poor and that doesn't have,
that doesn't have shame, דלא טיבזן de lo tivzan שתא בציר משני.
shata batzar mishnei. A year is taken out of his years. Okay,
so I'm not exactly sure what the idiom means, but it's sort
of saying like, you know, poverty follows the poor. All right? So,
so, so you know, so that's what they say because weavers are,
you know, they're,
they're shameless and therefore, and, and already they're poor and, you know,
bad things continue to happen to them. All right, anyway, תא חזי
ta chazi come and see מה בין גנבי בבל ולסטים דארץ ישראל.
ma bein ganvei Bavel u'listim d'Eretz Yisrael. Come see the difference between
the גנבים ganavim of בבל Bavel and the לסטים listim of ארץ
ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. In בבל, Bavel, the גנבים ganavim cursed רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda said he was a רמאי. ramai. In ארץ ישראל, Eretz
Yisrael, even the, even the robbers are פרום, frum, even the robbers
respect the rabbis and say, "Oh, you're תלמידים talmidim of רבי עקיבא,
Rebbi Akiva, you know, oh, praise be רבי עקיבא." Rebbi Akiva. Okay,
so we will end with this here.